Livingston-Fulton Family Papers, 1874-1939
Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College
Livingston-Fulton family papers
1874-1939
1920-1939
Livingston family
MS 147
6 boxes (2.4 linear ft.)
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
Collection consists primarily of the papers of Edith Livingston Crary Smith (1874-1938), author and poet. They document family matters and commentary on political and moral issues of the day. Material includes transcripts and other material pertaining to Smith's writings; also diaries and correspondence with her daughter, Katharine Smith Stevens and husband, Alpheus Dutton Smith.
Biographical Note
Edith Livingston Crary Roberts Smith was born in Poughkeepsie, New York on March 24, 1874 to Rev. Robert Fulton Crary and Agnes Boyd Van Kleeck. She attended Lyndon Hall in Poughkeepsie and subsequently taught there before marrying Charles Henry Van Braam Roberts on June 3, 1896. They had four children: Charles Van Braam Roberts (died in infancy), Edith "Toots" Livingston Roberts, Katharine "Watty" Bruce Roberts, and Richard "Wops" Brook Roberts. Mary van Kleeck, whose papers are also housed in the Sophia Smith Collection, was Smith's first cousin.
Smith's talent as a writer was apparent early on, and she published her first poem in 1892. According to her granddaughter, Smith began writing in earnest in 1902 or 1903 in order to leave an unhappy marriage and support her three surviving children. Although she regained some measure of financial security when she married Alpheus Dutton Smith circa 1903 (he legally adopted her children), she continued to write for twenty-five years, until poor health curtailed her ability to do so in the last decade of her life. She primarily wrote poetry, "pot boiler" short stories, and household advice columns for such publications as American Home Monthly, Good Housekeeping, Harper's Bazaar, House Beautiful, Ladies' Home Journal, Munsey's Magazine, The North American Review and Women's Home Companion.
In addition to freelance writing, Smith also worked for a time under Dr. Richard Cabot in the social services department of the Massachusetts General Hospital. Her experience there led her to write a series of related articles, most notably "Unmarried Mothers: One Big Job for the Feminist Movement," published in Harper's in 1913.
Edith Livingston Smith died on October 24, 1938 en route from Florida to New York on board the S.S. Shawnee. She was buried at sea.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The papers consist mainly of correspondence and material pertaining to Edith Livingston Crary Smith's writings. From 1920 to 1938, she wrote every day to her daughter, Katharine "Watty" Smith Stevens. The letters refer to family matters and personal musings, as well as to Smith's writing process and both her own and Watty's efforts to market their work. In addition, Alpheus Dutton Smith wrote almost daily when he and Smith were apart. His letters include commentary on the political and moral issues of the day, as well as discussion of personal and domestic concerns. The typescripts of Smith's writings reveal much about how she edited and revised her work, and about the writing process in general. Much of the material is annotated and in many cases includes several different versions of the same piece. Smith used her given name for serious work and the following pseudonyms for material which she considered to be less serious: Louise Chamberlayne, Daphne Deane, Stella Knight, Mrs. Livingston, Marjorie March, Wanda Moore, Marion Oakes, A. Singer, and Livingston Smith.
Also included in the papers is material supplied by Smith's granddaughter, Barbara Stevens Weeks, who provided extensive information about the family, particularly regarding the correspondents and the people referred to in the letters. She also researched Smith's published writings, furnishing virtually all bibliographic information.
Organization of the Collection
This collection is organized into four series:
I. Biographical
II. Diaries
III. Correspondence
IV. Writings
Oversize Materials
Information on Use
Terms of Access and Use
The papers are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection.
History of the Collection
Barbara Stevens Weeks donated the Edith Livingston Smith Papers to the Sophia Smith Collection in 1979, adding to them in 1995.
Search Terms
Smith, Edith Livingston Crary, 1874-1938; Mothers and daughters--United States--History--20th century--Sources; Women authors, American--20th century--Sources; Women poets, American--20th century--Sources; Cabot, Hugh, 1872-1945; Cabot, Richard C. (Richard Clarke), 1868-1939; Fulton Family; Livingston Family; Fulton Family
- SERIES I. BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIAL (1874-1939), 0.1 linear in.
- SERIES II. DIARIES (1919-36), 5 linear in.
  14 diaries with daily entries.
- SERIES III. CORRESPONDENCE (1885-1938), 10 linear in.
  Letters, hand-written and typed. Some hand-written letters have typescripts. Donor's notes are located at the beginning of the series.
- SERIES IV. WRITINGS (1892-29), 1.1 linear ft.
  Published writings cut from magazines, typescripts, booklet, scrapbook. Writings are arranged alphabetically by title. The donor's notes list the writings alphabetically, and also provide citations for published works. These are filed at the beginning of the Writings series, as well as before each sub-series.
- SERIES I. BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIAL (1874-1939)
  - Chronology, obituary, newspaper clippings 1874-1938, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Genealogyn.d. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Photographs 1883-1939, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 3)
- SERIES II. DIARIES (1919-36)
  - 1919-36 (Box 1, Folder 4-8)
- SERIES III. CORRESPONDENCE (1885-1938)
  - Notes on correspondence, compiled by donorn.d. (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - To Santa Clausn.d. (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - To and from family
    - To Alice Crary Sutcliffe 1885-1926 (Box 2, Folder 11-12)
    - To Katharine "Watty" Smith Stevens
      - 1913, 1920-31 (Box 2, Folder 13-26)
      - 1932-38 (Box 3, Folder 27-40)
    - From Alpheus Dutton Smith 1912-33, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 41-46)
    - To and from other family members 1926-38, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 47)
  - From friends and associates
    - From Dr. Hugh Cabot 1933-38 (Box 3, Folder 48)
    - From Dr. Richard Cabot 1923, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 49)
  - Third party
    - Alpheus Dutton Smith to Katharine "Watty" Smith Stevens 1923-38 (Box 3, Folder 50)
    - Carol Hahn to Katharine "Watty" Smith Stevens 1926 (Box 3, Folder 51)
  - Unidentified 1916, 1920 (Box 3, Folder 52)
- SERIES IV. WRITINGS (1892-29)
  - List of published and unpublished works, compiled by donorn.d. (Box 4, Folder 53)
  - Published works
    - Notes on books and short stories, compiled by donorn.d. (Box 4, Folder 54)
    - Books
      - A Garden of Yesterday, 1921
        [See also "Short stories"]
        - Photocopy of bookn.d. (Box 4, Folder 55)
        - Typescriptn.d. (Box 4, Folder 56)
    - Short stories
      - List compiled by donorn.d. (Box 4, Folder 57)
      - "A Garden of Yesterday" 1912 (Box 4, Folder 58)
      - Typescripts and published stories cut from magazines 1905-20 (Box 4, Folder 59-97)
    - Household advice articles
      - Notes compiled by donorn.d. (Box 4, Folder 98)
      - Artist's proofs and published articles cut from magazines 1902-06, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 99)
      - "The Woman's Exchange" 1906-09 (Box 4, Folder 100)
    - Social work articles
      - "Unmarried Mothers: One Big Job for the Feminist Movement" 1913 (Box 4, Folder 101)
      - Typescripts and published articles cut from magazines 1913, 1920, 1923, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 102)
    - Poetry
      - List compiled by donorn.d. (Box 4, Folder 103)
      - Notes and lists pertaining to poetry, by ELSn.d. (Box 4, Folder 104)
      - Booklet, Current Mother Goose: Timely Rhymes for Helpful Totsn.d. (Box 4, Folder 105)
      - Published poems cut from magazines 1892, 1902-21, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 106)
      - Typescripts, A-F (Box 4, Folder 107-110)
      - Typescripts, G-Y, untitledn.d. (Box 5, Folder 111-115)
      - Musical scoresn.d. (Box 5, Folder 116)
      - Scrapbook, published poems cut from magazines, newspaper clippings 1892-96, 1904-07, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 117)
      - Account book for published works 1901-11 (Box 5, Folder 118)
      - Poems by others, cut from magazinesn.d. (Box 5)
  - Unpublished works
    - List of unpublished works, compiled by donorn.d. (Box 5, Folder 119)
    - Books
      - According to Ma, 1910
        - Correspondence 1910-22 (Box 5, Folder 120)
        - Typescript, clean copyn.d. (Box 5, Folder 121)
        - Typescript, working copyn.d. (Box 5, Folder 122)
      - Untitled manuscriptca. 1910 (Box 5, Folder 123)
    - Short stories: typescripts, B-U, unidentified fragmentsn.d. (Box 6, Folder 124-125)
    - Household advice articles
      - List of household advice articles, compiled by donorn.d. (Box 6, Folder 126)
      - Typescripts, A-Vn.d. (Box 6, Folder 127-128)
- OVERSIZE MATERIALS
  [Located in Oversize Box 7]
  - Published short stories and household advice articles cut from magazines 1902-09 (Box 7)